Pepper Pike, Ohio. Trinity Congregational Church records, 1958-1983.
Congregational Library & Archives
Pepper Pike, Ohio. Trinity Congregational Church records, 1958-1983.
RG5532
Congregational Library & Archives
0.35 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
The Trinity Congregational Church was gathered in 1894. Construction of the first church building was completed in 1896. The community changed after World War I and the church building was sold with the intent of building a new building in Cleveland Heights. Construction on the second church building was completed in 1928. That building was sold in 1946 and a new building in Pepper Pike was constructed between 1951 and 1952. The church dissolved in 1983. This collection contains records and other documents related to the Trinity Congregational Church while it was in Pepper Pike. The collection contains annual reports, a copy of the church's constitution, membership directories, church records.
Trinity Congregational Church (Pepper Pike, Ohio)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Lyndhurst Community of Faith Church in July 2022; 2022-16.
Historical Note
The Trinity Congregational Church was gathered in 1894. Construction on the first church building was begun in 1895 and was located at Cedar Avenue at East 84th Street in Cleveland, Ohio. Construction of the church was completed in 1896 and the building was dedicated that same year. The community changed after World War I and the church building was sold with the intent of building a new building in Cleveland Heights. By 1927, land was purchased at Washington Boulevard at Thayne Road and construction of a new building was begun. The building was dedicated on Easter Sunday in 1928. The church struggled financially throughout World War II and by 1945 the neighborhood in Cleveland Heights had become majority Jewish. In 1946, the church building was sold to the Community Temple. In 1947, land for a new church building was purchased at Brainard Circle, Gates Mills Boulevard and Shaker Boulevard in Pepper Pike. Construction on the new building began in 1951 and was completed in 1952. A new wing for the church building was constructed between 1956 and 1957. The church was dissolved in 1983 and some proceeds from the sale of the church building were given to Faith United Church of Christ in Richmond Heights. 30 members of the church, as well as some of the church records, also went to the Faith United Church of Christ.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records and other documents related to the Trinity Congregational Church in Pepper Pike, Ohio. There are no records from before the church moved to Pepper Pike in this collection. The collection contains annual reports, church records, a 1964 copy of the church's constitution, membership directories, newsletters, a postcard depicting the interior of the church, and a pair of photographs recreating the Last Supper.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged into chronological order by start date. Contiguous folders have been maintained within the arrangement.
Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Religious newspapers and periodicals.; Pepper Pike (Ohio) -- Church history.; Trinity Congregational Church (Pepper Pike, Ohio)
- Miscellaneous church records, 1952 1974; 1952-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Church history, 1958 1959; 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Constitution, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual reports, 1965 1975; 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual reports, 1974 1983; 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Committee reports, 1967 1969; 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Postcard, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Membership directories, 1973 1982; 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Church records, 1974 1983; 1974, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Last Supper recreation photographs, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Link newsletters, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)